Guide to the Olga Scherer-Virski Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Olga Scherer-Virski papers
1954-1988
GEN MSS 526
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.5
(7 boxes)
The collection consists of correspondence, writings, and personal papers documenting the life and work of Olga Scherer-Virski. There is personal and professional correspondence with Polish literary and cultural figures, other Polish emigres, publishers, and scholars. Correspondents include Jozef Czapski, Witold Gombrowicz, Julia Hartwig, Zbigniew Herbert, Gustaw Herling-Grudzinski, Zofia Hertz, Aleksander Janta, Konstanty Jelenski, Andrej Kijowski, Jan Lebenstein, Artur Miedzyrzecki, Czeslaw Milosz, Slawomir Mrozek, Zofia Romanowiczowa, Alexander Schenker, Jerzy Stempowski, Adam Wazyk, and Jozef Wittlin. Writings include several translations of poems from Polish to French, and subject files include clippings on Gombrowicz, Jelenski, Milosz, and Aleksander Wat.
Scherer-Virski, Olga
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Olga Scherer-Virski Papers were acquired by purchase in 1990 on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 6-7: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
OLGA SCHERER-VIRSKI (1927-2001)
Olga Scherer-Virski was a Polish writer, literary scholar, and translator. She was born in Cracow, Poland, educated in the United States, where she completed her Ph.D. at Columbia University in 1952, and then held research affiliations and teaching positions at various institutions in the U.S. and France, including Bard College (1946-48,) Yale University (1953-57), Indiana University (1959-60), the Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique (1961-65), and the Université de Paris (1969-). She is the author of The Modern Polish Short Story (1955), a novella for children ( Spot Luck, 1957), and two novels, Wesolych Swiat (1962) and W Czas Morowy (1967). She also translated Manfred Kridl's A Survey of Polish Literature and Culture (1956).
Biographical information taken from Who's Who in the World (8th ed.) and the online Gale Biography Resource Center.
Scope and Contents
The Olga Scherer-Virski Papers consist of letters, manuscripts, and personal papers documenting the life and work of Olga Scherer-Virski. The collection spans the years 1954-1988.
The collection is housed in 7 boxes and organized into two series: Correspondence and Other Papers. Boxes 5-7 contain Oversize, Restricted Fragile Papers, and Restricted Fragile Oversize material respectively.
Series I, Correspondence, is organized into two subseries: General Correspondence and Third Party Correspondence.
The collection consists chiefly of incoming letters from well over 50 correspondents, including Polish literary figures of the second half of the 20th century. The collection provides information on the lives of Scherer and other Polish authors of the period, many of whom lived in exile in Europe and the Americas. The principal correspondents include Witold Gombrowicz, Zbigniew Herbert, Gustaw Herling-Grudzinski, Konstanty Jelenski, and Czeslaw Milosz.
Letters from Gombrowicz (1954-68) revolve around Scherer's attempts to translate and publish some of Gombrowicz's writings in English and French. Gombrowicz writes in a light tone, suggesting possible arrangements for the translation of his works, as well as repeatedly pointing to his extremely difficult financial situation as a Polish emigré author living in Argentina. The folder includes several outgoing letters.
Correspondence with Zbigniew and Katarzyna Herbert (1964-86) is friendly in nature and deals with visits of major Polish emigré figures, the literary work of several members of the circle, and relevant cultural events. There is a letter to Scherer from the Swedish Academy asking for her nomination for the Nobel Prize for Literature for the year 1984. Scherer nominates Zbigniew Herbert, pointing to the significance of his poetic series Mr. Cogito.
Letters from Gustaw Herling-Grudzinski (1964-81) are brief but friendly. Posted mainly from Naples, Italy, they focus on personal issues, as well as on the literary work of numerous Polish writers, including Mrozek, Gombrowicz, and Scherer.
Konstanty Jelenski (1962-87) was probably Scherer's closest friend among the correspondents represented in the collection. Jelenski advises Scherer on such subjects as health and emotional well-being, Scherer's relationship with Jan Lebenstein, writing, and translation. The folders include letters from Rena Jelenska, as well as a letter from Scherer summarizing her biographical information.
The three folders of letters from Czeslaw and Janka Milosz (1958-85) sketch a fascinating portrayal of the professional and personal concerns of the Polish Nobel Prize winner. Czeslaw Milosz writes in a rather somber tone, and ponders his role as a father, a husband, and also as a writer, teacher, and promoter of Polish literature in the U.S.
Other noteworthy correspondents in the collection include the painters Jan Lebenstein and Jozef Czapski; the journalist Aleksander Janta; Joseph Sadzik, a priest, publisher, and philosopher; Zofia Hertz, a key figure of the Polish Literary Institute in Paris; and various literary critics, scholars, and writers: Andrzej Kijowski, Zofia Kozarynowa, Artur Miedzyrzecki and Julia Hartwig, Slawomir Mrozek, Zofia Romanowicz, Alexander Schenker, Jerzy Stempowski, Adam Wazyk, and Jozef Wittlin.
There are also several outgoing letters whose style justifies Scherer's reputation as a "grande dame" of Polish letters. Czeslaw Milosz identified Scherer as the link between Poland and the Polish Parisian circle revolving around the journal Kultura. As the poet pointed out, Scherer was not only a literary scholar, but also a writer, one whose novels might be described as "campus" fiction in the vein of the works of Mary McCarthy or David Lodge. Outgoing letters are indicated in folder notes in the box list.
Third Party Correspondence, housed in box 4, contains four pieces of correspondence, and includes letters to Jelenski from Gombrowicz and Kijowski.
Series II, Other Papers, also housed in box 4, is organized into three small subseries: Writings, Subject Files, and Other Papers.
Of note in the Writings are Scherer's manuscript notes and fragments concerning translations of several Polish poems into French, including "Jaka spadnie kara" by Mickiewicz and "Bog mi odmowil..." by Krasinski. The Subject Files consist chiefly of clippings on Gombrowicz, Jelenski, Milosz, and Wat.
Oversize material, housed in box 5, contains items from Series I. Restricted Fragile Papers and Restricted Fragile Oversize are housed in boxes 6 and 7 respectively.
Authors, Polish -- 20th Century -- Archives; European literature -- 20th Century; Polish literature -- 20th Century; Poland; Authors; Czapski, Józef, 1896-1993; Gombrowicz, Witold, 1904-1969; Hartwig, Julia, 1921-; Herbert, Zbigniew, 1924-1998; Herling-Grudziński, Gustaw, 1919-2000; Hertz, Zofia; Janta, Aleksander, 1908-1974; Jeleński, Konstanty A. (Konstanty Aleksander), 1922-1987; Kijowski, Andrzej, 1928-1985; Lebenstein, Jan, 1930-1999; Międzyrzecki, Artur, 1922-1996; Miłosz, Czesław, 1911-2004; Mrożek, Sławomir, 1930-2013; Romanowiczowa, Zofia, 1922-2010; Schenker, Alexander M., 1924-; Scherer-Virski, Olga; Stempowski, Jerzy, 1894-1969; Wat, Aleksander, 1900-1967; Ważyk, Adam, 1905-1982; Wittlin, Józef, 1896-1976
- Correspondence, 1954-1988; Series I; 1.34; (3.5 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Correspondence, is organized into two subseries, General Correspondence and Third Party Correspondence.
  - GENERAL CORRESPONDENCE
    - "A" General, 1974 May 21 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "B" General, 1955-87 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Bednaryk, Czeslaw; Bednaryk, Krystyna, 1966-67 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Biczycki, Jan, 1962-77 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Brandys, Kazimierz; Brandys, Marysia, 1971-87, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5-7)
    - Brzozowski, Tadeusz, 1961, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "C" General, 1964, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Carroll-Najder, Halina
      Related Archival Materials note
      See: Najder, Zdzislaw, Box 2, folder 56
    - Chmielowiec, Michal
      See: Wiadomosci, Box 3, folder 87
    - Czapski, Jozef, 1971-87, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Includes letter from Maria Czapski
    - Dziennik Polski, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - "E" General, 1964 Nov 11 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Erlich, Victor, 1965 Dec 23 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - "F" General, 1965 Dec (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Gombrowicz, Witold, 1954-68, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Includes letters from Scherer to Gombrowicz
      See also: Simon and Schuster, Box 3, folder 77
    - Gren, Zygmunt, 1969-76, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Guze, Joanna, 1972 Dec 29 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - "H" General, 1967, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 18)
      Includes art exhibition catalog
    - Hartwig, Julia
      See: Miedzyrzecki, Artur, Box 2, folder 51
    - Herbert, Zbigniew; Herbert, Katarzyna, 1964-86, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 19-21)
    - Herling-Grudzinski, Gustaw, 1964-81, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 22-23)
    - Hertz, Zygmunt; Hertz, Zofia, 1962-72, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Hordynski, Jerzy, 1964-66 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Iwaniuk, Waclaw, 1960-83, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 26)
      Includes enclosure
    - Janta, Aleksander, 1957-71 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      Includes letters from Scherer to Janta
    - Jelenski, Konstanty A. (Konstanty Aleksander); Jelenska, Rena, 1962-87, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 28-34)
      Includes letters from Scherer and [Jerzy?] Stempowski to Jelenski and enclosures
    - [Jovanovich, William?], n.d. (Box 2, Folder 35)
      Includes letter in Milosz's hand
    - "K" General, 1965-77 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Karpinski, Wojciech, 1972 Aug 16 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Kijowski, Andrzej; Kijowska, Kazimiera, 1961-86, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 38-39)
    - Kisielewski, Stefan, 1972-76 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Korzeniewski, Tadeusz, 1985 Apr 26 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Kosko, Allan, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - [Kowalewski, J.?], 1964-65 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Kozarynowa, Zofia, 1963-77 (Box 2, Folder 44-45)
      Includes clippings
    - Kridl, Manfred, 1954-55 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Krzyzanowski, Ludwik, 1956-57
      See: Polish Institute of Arts and Sciences in America, Box 2, folder 63
    - Kultura, 1967-82 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - "L" General, 1964 Nov (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Lebenstein, Jan; Lebenstein, Maria, 1964-71, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 49)
      Includes letters from Scherer to Jan Lebenstein
    - "M" General, 1962, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Miedzyrzecki, Artur; Hartwig, Julia, 1974-87, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Milosz, Czeslaw; Milosz, Janka, 1958-85, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 52-54)
      Includes letter to Milosz from "The Wilson Center" and clipping
      See also: Jovanovich, William, Box 2, folder 35
    - Mrozek, Slawomir, 1970-73 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Muzeum Literatury im. Adama Mickiewicza w Warszawie
      See: Odrowaz-Pieniazek, Janusz, Box 2, folder 58
    - Najder, Zdzislaw; Carroll-Najder, Halina, 1967-83, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 56)
      Includes photograph
    - Nowakowski, Tadeusz, 1963-77 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Odrowaz-Pieniazek, Janusz, 1964-80 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - Osiecka, Agnieszka, 1978 Jan 6 (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - "P" General, 1955-86 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Paczkowska, Irena, 1961-62, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Piotrowski, [Jacek?], 1961 Jan 15 (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - Polish Institute of Arts and Sciences in America, 1956-57 (Box 2, Folder 63)
      Includes carbon of letter from Scherer to Polish Institute
    - Romanowicz, Zofia, 1961-82, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - Rostworowski, Jan, 1967 Jun 7 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - "S" General, 1977, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - Sadzik, Jozef, 1965-80, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 67-71)
    - Schaff, Adam, 1964-67 (Box 3, Folder 72)
    - Schenker, Aleksander; Schenker, Elaine; Schenker, Krystyna, 1963-86, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 73-75)
      Includes third-party letter to Scherer and photograph
    - Sédir, Georges, 1967, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 76)
    - Simon and Schuster, Inc., 1957-58 (Box 3, Folder 77)
      Includes carbons of letters from Scherer to Simon and Schuster and Witold Gombrowicz
    - Solski, Waclaw, 1948-79 (Box 3, Folder 78)
    - Stempowski, Jerzy, 1961-67, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 79)
    - Svenska Akademien, 1983-84 (Box 3, Folder 80)
      Includes carbon of letter from Scherer to Svenska Akademien
    - "T" General, 1977, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 81)
    - Tatarkiewicz, [Wladyslaw?], 1973 Oct 7 (Box 3, Folder 82)
      Carbon of letter from Scherer to Tatarkiewicz
    - Urbanski, Edmund [Stefan?], 1947 Oct 22 (Box 3, Folder 83)
    - Wazyk, Adam, 1967-80, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 84)
    - Watowa, Ola, 1966-1967, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 85)
      Includes clipping
    - Weintraub, Wiktor, 1962, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 86)
    - Wiadomosci, 1955-71 (Box 3, Folder 87)
      Includes carbons of letters from Scherer to Wiadomosci and enclosure
    - Wierzynski, Kazimierz; Wierzynska, Halina, 1955-74, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 88)
    - Winczakiewicz, J[an?], 1963-66, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 89)
    - Winnicka, Wanda, 1966-67, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 90)
    - Wittlin, Jozef; Wittlin, Halina, 1958-71 (Box 4, Folder 91)
    - Wlodek, Jozef, 1964 Mar 17 (Box 4, Folder 92)
    - Woodrow Wilson International Center for Scholars
      See: Milosz, Czeslaw, Box 2, folders, 52-54
    - World Literature Today, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 93)
    - Woroszylski, Wiktor, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 94)
      Includes carbon of letter from Scherer to Woroszylski
    - Wozniakowska, Roza, 1979-81 (Box 4, Folder 95)
    - Zelenski, Wladyslaw, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 96)
    - Unidentified, 1962-87, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 97)
  - THIRD PARTY CORRESPONDENCE
    - Gombrowicz, Witold to Konstanty Jelenski, 1968 Aug 24 (Box 4, Folder 98)
    - Kijowski, Andrzej to Konstanty Jelenski (Box 4, Folder 99)
    - Kozarynowa, Zofia to Zofia Romanowicz, 1977 May 5 (Box 4, Folder 100)
    - Miedzyrzecki, Artur to Barbara Majewska, 1978 Feb 8 (Box 4, Folder 101)
      Includes note from Julia Hartwig
- Other Papers, 1960-1987; Series II; 0.11; (.5 box)
  Series II, Other Papers, is organized into three subseries: Writings, Subject Files, and Other Papers
  - WRITINGS
    - Writings of Olga Scherer-Virski
      - Manuscript notes and fragments, holograph and typescript, corrected (Box 4, Folder 102)
        Includes translations of work by Antoni Malczewski, Adam Mickiewicz, Krasinski, and Witwicki
      - "Trente-six Poetes Polonais," preface for Preuves, typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 103)
    - Writings of Others
      Iwaniuk, Waclaw
      - Iwaniuk, Waclaw
        - Untitled poem, typescript, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 104)
      - Jelenski, Konstanty
        - "Reponse a des critiques partisans," article, photocopy, 1966 Apr (Box 4, Folder 105)
      - Kijowski, Andrzej
        - [Urodzilem sie 29 listopada..."], autobiographical statement, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 106)
      - McCarthy, Mary
        "Constantin Jelenski, l'ami Kot," article, printed version, Liberation
        See: Subject Files, Jelenski, Box 6, folder 109
      - Milosz, Czeslaw
        "L'hommage de Milosz à Jelenski," article, printed version, Le Monde
      - Sandzig, Jozef
        - "Heidegger: le chemin de campagne," notes, holograph (Box 4, Folder 107)
  - SUBJECT FILES
    - Gombrowicz, Witold, 1978, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 108)
    - Jelenski, Konstanty A. (Konstanty Aleksander), 1987 (Box 4, Folder 109)
      Includes obituaries on Jelenski by Czeslaw Milosz and Mary McCarthy
    - Milosz, Czeslaw, 1978-79 (Box 4, Folder 110)
    - Wat, Aleksander, 1967 Aug 23 (Box 4, Folder 111)
  - OTHER PAPERS
    - Address for [Wencslas?] Godlewski, [1961?] (Box 4, Folder 112)
    - Printed ephemera for conference on Maria Konopnicka, 1960 Sep (Box 4, Folder 113)
    - Stamps, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 114)
- Oversize, 0.92; (1 box)
  - Letters from Czeslaw and Krystyna Bednaryk to Scherer (In Series I), 1966-67 (Box 5, Folder 115)
- Restricted Fragile Papers, 0.21; (1 box)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 2, folder 44 (Box 6, Folder 116)
  - Box 3, folder 67 (Box 6, Folder 117)
  - Box 3, folder 75 (Box 6, Folder 118)
  - Box 3, folder 79 (Box 6, Folder 119)
  - Box 4, folder 92 (Box 6, Folder 120)
  - Box 4, folder 109 (Box 6, Folder 121)
  - Box 4, folder 110 (Box 6, Folder 122)
- Restricted Fragile Oversize, 0.92; (1 box)
  - Box 2, folder 45 (Box 7, Folder 123)
  - Box 4, folder 109 (Box 7, Folder 124)
  - Box 4, folder 111 (Box 7, Folder 125)